Hi. I'm Stephen, I'm a content developer here at Udacity.
こんにちはスティーブンです Udacity のコース開発者です
I've worked on the system integration content and I run code on Carla.
私はシステム統合コンテンツに取り組んでおり Carla でコードを実行しています
Hi. I'm Aaron Brown,
こんにちはアーロン ブラウンです
I'm a Content Developer here for self-driving car and I
自動運転車のコンテンツ開発者で
worked on the simulation portion for
キャップストーン プロジェクトのシミュレーション部分
this capstone project that we're walking you through today.
に携わりました
Let's go ahead and get started.
では始めましょう
We're going to be doing the project walk-through,
プロジェクトのチュートリアルを行います
this is a project walk-through that we'll be doing in four steps.
これはプロジェクトのチュートリアルであり 4 つのステップで行います
So, the first step today is the first part of the waypoint updating.
今日の最初のステップは ウェイポイント更新の最初の部分です
Yeah, that's right. So, we want to be able to see these waypoints on
そうですねそれで 道路上でこれらのウェイポイントを見て
the road and eventually try to get this car to follow.
車両を追跡することを試みることができるようになりたいと思っています
Yeah, hopefully.
そう願います
Yeah. So, let's go ahead and check out the classroom and see what we need to get started.
はい先に進んで クラスルームをチェックアウトし 開始するために必要なものを見てみましょう
Right away, I'm seeing that I need Ubuntu and ROS.
今のところ Ubuntu と ROS が必要なのが分かります
There's actually a way to run this project natively if you have Linux or Windows even,
Linux や Windows さえあれば 実際にこのプロジェクトをネイティブに実行する方法があります
I used Ubuntu Bash.
私は Ubuntu Bash を使用しました
If you don't have either of those,
両方とも持っていない場合
there's a VM that you can use and that's for if you're running on a Mac for instance.
Mac 上で実行可能な VM などがあります
But, ROS and Ubuntu are the big things
ROS と Ubuntu は有名ですが
and there's DBW Node as well that I can see on here.
DBW Node も見ることができます
So, what is DBW Node?
DBW Node とは何でしょうか?
So, DBW is drive-by wire,
DBW はドライブ バイ ワイヤーで
that's the node that runs in the car and allows
自動車内で稼働し
the ROS to interface with the car's hardware.
ROS が自動車のハードウェアと連動することを可能にするノードです
So, it allows ROS to actually actuate the car's steering and throttle.
それで ROS が実際に自動車のステアリングとスロットルを作動させることを可能にします
Okay. So, that's our bridge then between the hardware and software.
OKこれは ハードウェアとソフトウェアの間の橋渡しをするものです
And the reason you need to install it for this project is that it
このプロジェクトのために これをインストールする必要がある理由は
contains ROS message definitions that you'll be needing for the code.
コードのために必要となるであろう ROS メッセージ定義が含まれるからです
So, once I have all that installed,
それで 一度すべてをインストールすると
I can go ahead and get started by checking out the repository,
先に進み リポジトリをチェックアウトすることから始めることができます
and that'll have all the files I need to get running
VM にアクセスできるようにするために
to take me right to the VM and then here,
実行する必要があるすべてのファイルが手に入り
I can actually go to the capstone project.
その後 実際にキャップストーン プロジェクトに進むことができます
This should have instructions for how to run the ROS code and
これには ROS コードの実行方法と
how to install the DBW software.
DBW ソフトウェアのインストール方法に関する指示があります
Okay. So, it's just like any other project where I'm just cloning down the repo,
OKこれは リポジトリを複製する他のプロジェクトと同じです
here's some special instructions for getting it set up, going into ROS,
ここには セットアップして ROS に入るための特別な指示があります
running catkin_make, source devil setup.sh,
catkin_make を実行し devil setup.sh を起動すると
and then ROS will launch.
ROS が起動します
So, what's one of the first files I need to start modifying and get this project working.
修正を始めて このプロジェクトを動かすために必要な最初のファイルの1つは何でしょうか?
So, the first thing that you're going to need to do is to modify the Waypoint Updater.
しなければならないことは ウェイポイント アップデーターを修正することです
So, we want to go to Waypoint Updater Node partial.
Waypoint Updater Node (Partial) に進みましょう
So, in this, basically we have some base waypoints,
基本的にいくつかのベースとなるウェイポイントがあり
so we're publishing a lane object that has
自動車が追従するウェイポイントのリストを含む
some information including list of waypoints that the car will be following.
情報を持つ車線オブジェクトを公開しています
And what you want to do is use the current position of the car,
current_pose トピックにくる
which comes in over the current_pose topic,
車両の現在位置を使いたい場合
and then publish the waypoints that are ahead of the car.
車両の前方にあるウェイポイントを公開します
Those will be your final waypoints.
最終的に 4 つのウェイポイントがあります
All right, should we go ahead and check out the file?
先に進んで ファイルをチェック アウトしますか?
Sure.
はい
All right, so this is what the file looks like when you first load it up.
最初にファイルをロードしたときにファイルがどのように見えるかです
I see that there's some waypoints ahead,
いくつかのウェイポイントがあり
there's 200 by default.
デフォルトでは 200 です
So, those are the first 200 waypoints in front of the car.
車両の前方には 最初に 200 個のウェイポイントがあります
So, I'm using this subscriber to get these base waypoints,
ベースウェイポイントを得るために、このサブスクライバーを使っています
so how do I get a chunk of those base waypoints?
どうやって基本的なウェイポイントのセットを取得できますか?
So, you said you're using a subscriber there,
加入者を使用しており
and the base waypoints if you look at the rospy subscriber,
rospy.Subscriberを見ると
it has base waypoints, that's the topic.
基本的なウェイポイントがある場合は トピックになります
Lane is the message type that's coming over the topic.
Laneはトピックのメッセージタイプです
Then, waypoints_cb is the waypoints callback,
次に waypoints_cb はウェイポイント コールバックです
that's the function that basically gets called every time.
これは 基本的に毎回呼ばれる関数です
Right here.
ここです
Yeah.
はい
Okay. So, we need to implement that.
OKこれを実装する必要があります
We need to make sure that this is able to receive these waypoints.
ウェイポイントを受信できることを確認する必要があります
Yeah, basically you just want to store them.
基本的にはウェイポイントを保存したいだけです
Shall we take a look at the result.
結果を見てみましょう
Sure.
はい
Okay.
OK
So, if we scroll down to waypoints callback.
ウェイポイントをコールバックするまでスクロール ダウンするとします
There's the callback function.
Callback 関数があります
Yeah. So, in the callback, we have the waypoints,
はいコールバックには
which were coming in and
受信するウェイポイントがあり
self.basewaypoints equals waypoints basically just stores these in the object.
self.basewaypoints は ウェイポイントとオブジェクトに保存するだけです
Okay. So, this is a subscriber,
OKこれは加入者です
does that mean this is happening every single time.
これが毎回起こっていることを意味しますか?
Normally yes, but this is a latched subscriber.
通常は はいです しかし これはラッチされた加入者です
I believe that's the way the code is currently set up in the repo,
コードが現在リポジトリに設定されている方法であると信じています
so once callback is called it doesn't send the base waypoints anymore.
一度、コールバックが呼び出されるとbase_waypointsは送信されなくなります
That's good, because the base waypoints are never changing,
これは良いことです
so that'd be really inefficient,
base_waypointsは変更されないので
just calling that certain number of times every second.
毎秒何回も呼び出すのは非効率的です
So, it only calls them once.
そのため 一度 関数を呼び出します
Then, we have some other code in here that's doing some interesting things.
ここには他にも面白いコードを書いたコードがあります
So, the basic idea is that we want to take a chunk of
したがって 基本的な考え方は これらの基本的なウェイポイントのセットを取得し
these base waypoints and use the first 200 that are in front of the car as reference.
車両の正面にある最初の 200個 を参照として使用することです
So, what's a great way of actually figuring out which waypoint is closest to the car.
どのウェイポイントが車両に最も近いか実際に考え出す素晴らしい方法は何ですか?
So, that's a good question.
良い質問です
In this code, we're using something called the KDTree.
このコードでは KDTree と呼ばれるものを使用しています
Where does KDTree come from?
KDTree は どこから来ますか?
Oh, it's up here in scipy.
Scripy にあります
Correct, so we've imported scipy.spatial import KDTree.
正解です scipy.spatial import KDTree をインポートしました
KDTree is a data structure that'll allow you to
KDTree は 空間内の最も近い点を効率的に検索できるようにする
look up the closest point in space really efficiently.
データ構造を備えています
So, that's like log n instead of n.
n ではなく log n のようなものです
Yeah. So, if you were to search directly through the list of waypoints.
はいウェイポイントのリストを通して直接検索する場合です
You get a thousand waypoints maybe the waypoint it wants at the very end of that list.
1000 個のウェイポイントがあるかもしれません おそらく リストの最後に欲しいウェイポイントです
Yeah, it'll take a long time.
はい 長い時間がかかります
If I'm using a KDTree and if it's like log n and maybe it's only 10 cycles to find it,
KDTree を使用し log nのようなものであり 10 サイクルしかないのであれば
that's way more efficient.
効率性は高くなります
So, this is a much better way to do that.
これは はるかに良い方法です
Cool. So, we're using this KDTree,
素晴らしいKDTree を使用しています
how do we set up this KDTree?
この KDTree をどのように設定しますか?
Down here, you can see that in the code we've converted
ここでは コード内でウェイポイントを
the waypoints to just the 2D coordinates for each waypoint.
各ウェイポイントの 2D 座標に変換したことがわかります
So, it's a list of comprehension here.
これは 理解のためのリストです
We have for each waypoint and waypoints.waypoints.
ウェイポイントごとに waypoints.waypoints があります
We have waypoint.pose.pose.position.x and waypoint.pose.pose.position.y.
waypoint.pose.pose.position.x と waypoint.pose.pose.position.yがあります
So, this will give us a list of a bunch of 2D coordinates for each waypoint.
各ウェイポイントのための 2D 座標のセットのリストが提供されます
We use that to construct a KDTree.
これは KDTree を構築するために使用します
Awesome. So, we've done that with
素晴らしい一回のコールバックで
a single callback and now what other information are we getting from subscribers.
購読者から得られる その他の情報で構築しました
I think an important one is probably the pose of the car.
重要なのは おそらく車両のポーズだと思います
Yeah. Actually one thing I wanted to mention about this callback down there,
はい実際には このコールバックについて言及したいことが 1 つあります
we have the code if not
ここでは self.waypoints2D ではないコードがあります
self.waypoints2D because that attribute is being used in the callback here,
また ここでは その属性がコールバックで使用されているため
we want to make sure that that self.waypoints2D is initialized before the subscriber is.
2D が加入者より前に初期化されるようにします
Otherwise, you could run into some risk conditions where
そうしないとwaypoints_2dが初期化される前に
the subscriber callback is called before waypoints2D is initialized.
サブスクライバーコールバックが呼び出されるというリスク条件に遭遇する可能性があります
And then, it doesn't know what to reference and then you're going to have some problems.
何を参照すればよいのかわからないので 問題が発生します
Yeah, that makes sense.
よくわかりました
So, we have this other callback for pose_cb,
pose_cb のためのコールバックがあり
and that's just grabbing what the pose is.
ポーズが何であるかを把握しています
So, just stores the car's pose.
そのため 車両のポーズを保存します
It's that's simple enough.
答えはシンプルです
That one gets called frequently.
これは頻繁に呼び出されます
How often?
どれほどの頻度ですか?
I don't know exactly, but it's probably around 50 hertz.
正確にはわかりませんが おそらく 50 ヘルツ前後です
Cool. So, we have those two things to work from,
素晴らしい2 つの作業があります
now in the beginning file we have something else that looks like this with rospy.spin,
今度は最初のファイルに rospy.spin を使って このように見える何かがあります
for this results in code that we're talking about,
この結果 私達が話しているコードになりますが
it looks quite different. Here, there's a loop.
かなり違って見えますここにループがあります
So, we've defined a loop function that gives us,
それで ループ関数を定義し
basically the reason we're doing this is because this
基本的にこれを行っているのは
gives us control over the publishing frequency.
パブリッシュの頻度を制御するためです
Okay. So, we want to target 50 hertz.
OK50 ヘルツを目標とします
Sure. You could probably get away with something
はいこの場合 おそらく 50 ヘルツより少し小さくて
a little bit less than 50 hertz in this case.
問題ありません
The final waypoints which we'll be publishing go to the waypoint follower,
公開する最後のウェイポイントは
which is a piece of code from Autoware,
Autoware のコードの一部であるウェイポイント フォロワーに公開し
and I believe that's running at 30 hertz.
30 ヘルツで実行されていると考えられます
So, you could probably go as low as 30 hertz and less
これらのメッセージは、30ヘルツで実行される
because these messages are going to go straight over to waypoint follower,
waypoint follower に行くだけなので
which is cycling at 30 hertz in them onto your drive by wire.
30ヘルツまたはそれ未満まで下げることも可能です
So, we got that loop that's constantly happening at
そのループは 50 ヘルツで絶えず起こっているため
50 hertz and let's see what's going on here.
ここで何が起こっているのか見てみましょう
So, if we have pose and base waypoints,
pose と base_waypoints があれば
those are the two things we're just talking about.
それは 今話している 2 つのことです
A lot of rospy is not shut down,
多くの rospy はシャットダウンされていないため
this is what we're going to be executing.
これが実行しているものです
So, we need to get that closest waypoint.
そのため 最も近いウェイポイントを取得する必要があります
So, we're using this function right here to
この関数を使って
get_closest_waypoint and then we're going to be using that KDTree,
get_closest_waypoint を取得し KDTree を使うことになります
let's just go ahead and pick at that.
進み ウェイポイントを選びます
So, get_closest_waypoint.
そのため get_closest_waypoint を実行します
Yeah. So, in get_closest_waypoint,
はいget_closest_waypoint においては
we get the coordinates of our car.
車両の座標を取得します
So, that's self.pose.pose.position.x and sel.pose.pose.position.y,
self.pose.pose.position.x と sel.pose.pose.position.y です
and if you're confused about how many poses you need
position.xy に到着する前に置く必要がある ポーズの
to put in before you get to position.x.y,
数で悩む場合
the best thing is to go look at the message definitions for that type of message.
最善策は その種類のメッセージのメッセージ定義を調べることです
I know it's.pose.pose and not just.pose.
it's.pose.pose は知っていますが just.pose は知りません
So, if you look at the message definition it should be pretty clear.
メッセージの定義を見れば かなり明確なはずです
There's definitely some instruction in the classroom on how to check out those messages?
メッセージをチェック アウトする方法について 教室において 指示がありますか?
Yes, in the concept for this Waypoint Updater Node, it talks about-
はい、このWaypoint Updater Nodeのコンセプトでは、
ROStopics and ROSmessages.
rostopic と rosmsg について話しています
So, you can use ROS message info to get more info about that particular message type?
それで 特定のメッセージ タイプについて より多くの情報を得るために ROS メッセージ情報を使うことができますか?
Yeah, and I can kind of come down here and I can see
はい ここで 詳しく見てみると
how this is all formatted for waypoints.
ウェイポイントのためにフォーマットされている方法を見ることができます
All of the messages, I believe,
すべてのメッセージは
are in the six folder in the project report.
プロジェクト レポートの 6 つのフォルダーにあります
So all the message deficit.
それで すべてのメッセージに不足があります
This is how it knows pose dot pose,cool.
ここを見れば、pose.poseだとわかります いいね
So, then we're just doing a query on this tree based on an x and y gives us back one.
では xとyに基づいて このツリーに対してクエリを実行します
So, we have this array that's returning us and we have this,
それで 返却されている配列があります
I'm guessing some sort of distance away and then also the index itself.
ある種の距離 そして インデックス自体も推測しています
So exactly what you said. The first one there does we only want to return one item.
それこそ いま述べたことです最初のものは 1 つのアイテムを返したいだけです
So, the closest point in our TB tree to our query item.
そのため TB ツリー内でクエリ アイテムに最も近い点です
The second one there, as you said,
2 番目の 1 によって
that the query will return the position and also the index,
クエリが位置とインデックスを返されます
and the index is in the same order as you put into the K-D tree.
インデックスはK-Dツリーに入れたのと同じ順序です
So, we put in all those 2D coordinates for waypoints and
それで ウェイポイント用にこれらすべての二次元座標を入力します
so what we're trying to get is basically the index of that coordinate.
したがって 取得しようとしているのは基本的にその座標のインデックスです
Right, closest index is what we care about.
正しいです 最も近いインデックスに注意します
Let's see what happens next.
次に起こる点を見てみましょう
Closest coordinate.
最も近い座標です
So, that's from waypoints 2D,
これはウェイポイント 2D からのもので
and then we're just grabbing that waypoint 2D,
ウェイポイント2Dを取得しただけで
and then we have the previous coordinate as well.
前の座標も取得できます
So, we're doing a little bit of math here,
ここでは ちょっとした計算をしています
because we're talking about that we wanted to make sure
なぜなら これらのウェイポイントが車の前にあることを確認したいと思ったからです
these waypoints were in front of the car, right?
よろしいですか?
Yeah. So, we're trying to figure out,
はい私たちは
we've got the closest waypoint from the waypoint tree query,
waypoint_tree.query によって最も近いウェイポイントを取得しました
but we want to make sure that that point is in front of the car.
しかし そのポイントが自動車の前にあることを確認したいと考えています
So, we can use this kind of hyperplane
この種の超平面を使用してから内積を計算して
and then do a dot product to see that's positive or negative,
それが正または負であることを確認し
and based on that dot product between those two vectors,
2 つのベクトル間の内積に基づいて
we can see if that first waypoint is indeed is in front of the car or not.
最初のウェイポイントが実際に車両の正面にあるかどうかを確認できます
If it's behind the car,
ウェイポイントが車の背後になる場合
then we just ignore it and cut it off?
無視してそれを切り取るだけでよいですか?
Take the next one. So, if it is behind the car,
次のポイントを取りますウェイポイントが車両の背後にあり
if we've determined that the closest waypoint is behind us, we just take the next one.
最も近いウェイポイントが後ろにあると判断した場合 次のポイントを取ります
We take the next one, but we modulo the length of the total waypoint list.
次のポイントを取りますが ウェイポイント リスト全体の長さをモジュール化します
So, that's if down there in the code,
コードにおいて
if val is greater than zero,
val が 0 より大きい場合
meaning the way point is actually behind us,
ウェイポイントが背後にあることを意味しているため
then we take the closest index plus one,
最も近いインデックスプラス 1 を取りますが
but modulo the length of waypoints 2D.
ウェイポイント 2D の長さをモジュール化します
So, for this hyperplane,
したがって この超平面については
maybe we should talk a little bit about how this math works.
この数学がどのように機能するかについて少し話をする必要があります
Sure, yeah. So, we have a little diagram here.
はいここに小さな図があります
So, this is basically what's going on.
ここに基本的に起こっていることが示されています
So, here is our closest waypoint.
ここは 最も近いウェイポイントです
So, this one is Cl-vect right here.
それで これは Cl-vect です
Then, there is the previous waypoint.
次に 前のウェイポイントがあります
This arrow, this vector right here is
この矢印
the difference between its closest vector and previous vector.
ここにあるこのベクトルは 最も近いベクトルと前のベクトルの差です
That's our reference vector right there and it's
これが基準ベクトルであり
defining this hyperplane that's perpendicular to it.
垂直なこの超平面を定義しています
So, we have the hyperplane given by
破線で与えられる超平面があり
the dashed line and that should be perpendicular to this vector.
このベクトルに垂直であるべきです
Then the car can be either two possible states.
車は 2 つの状態のいずれかである場合もあります
It can be in front of this hyperplane or behind it?
超平面の前方または背後ですね？
So, here are the two possible states for our car.
この車は 2 つの状態にある可能性があります
So, pos_vect is there and pos_vect is there.
つまり pos_vect と pos_vect があります
If our car is in front of the closest waypoint,
車が最も近いウェイポイントの正面にある場合
so it's in front of this hyperplane determined by this vector.
車両は このベクトルによって決定される超平面の前に位置しています
Both vectors are pointing in the same direction.
両方のベクトルは同じ方向を向いています
Our closest index is actually behind the car.
最も近いインデックスは実際には車両の背部に位置します
This top product is positive.
このドットの積は正です
Yeah. On the other hand,
はい反対に
if our car's position is behind this hyperplane,
車両の位置が超平面の背後にある場合は
so it's behind the closest waypoint.
最も近いウェイポイントの背後にあることになります
Then, the opposite. They're pointing in
そのため 反対に位置します両は反対方向を示し
opposite directions and the dot product is negative.
内積は負です
Yep.
もちろんできます
Okay, so this is how we can tell if that
OK これが
closest waypoint is in front of the car or behind it.
最も近いウェイポイントが車両の前方 または 背後にあるかを示します
Yep and that's exactly what's going on in the code there.
はい まさにそこにコードで起こっていることです
Cool. Let's go over this math a little bit
素晴らしいこの超平面をどのように扱っているか 内積が正か負か
for how we're dealing with this hyperplane and figuring
この座標が車両の前にあるか
out if the dot product is
どうかを確認するために
positive or negative and if this coordinate's in front of us or not.
この数学をもう少し調べてみましょう
Yeah, so we get the closest vect there is our closest coordinate.
はい 最も近い座標がある最も近い vect を得ることができます
That's kind of this base coordinate we're using and it's all relative to that.
私たちが使っている基本座標のようなもので すべて相対的なものです
So that's 2D coordinate of the waypoint.
これが ウェイポイントの 2D 座標です
Then, we're just looking at where the car's at,
車の位置を見ているだけで
and we can draw a vector from that reference point to that car's position.
基準点からその車の位置までベクトルを描くことができます
So, previous vect, that's the previous coordinate here, and position vect.
ここの前の座標である以前の vect と vect を配置します
That's at x y, and then we're just kind of looking at how this is aligning.
x y にあり これがどのように整列しているかを見ているようなものです
You can use the car's orientation, waypoints orientation,
車両の向き ウェイポイントの向きを使用でき
you can create a vector from the previous waypoint to
前のウェイポイントから現在のウェイポイントまでのベクトル
the current waypoint and use
を作成し
the car's orientation to see if they're facing in the same direction.
車両の方向を使って 同じ方向を向いているかどうかを確認できます
So, this is just one possible way.
これは 一つの可能な方法にすぎません
Then we return that closest index after that,
最も近いインデックスを返し
and we can kind of come back up and see what's going on.
戻って来たもので 何が起こっているのか見ることができます
So, then we're just publishing these waypoints.
それで これらのウェイポイントを公開しています
Closest waypoint index.
closest_waypoint_idx
So, now we go down to the published waypoints function.
今度は公開されているウェイポイント関数に行きます
We have our closest index and the index of the closest waypoint ahead of the car,
最も近いインデックスと車の前に最も近いウェイポイントのインデックスを持っているため
and so what we do, the message type needs to be a lane.
メッセージ タイプは車線である必要があります
So, we create a new lane object,
それで 新しい車線オブジェクト
or a new lane message,
または新しい車線メッセージを作成します
and the lane header is the same as the base waypoints header.
車線ヘッダーは基本ウェイポイント ヘッダーと同じです
Doesn't really matter, we're not going to use the header.
実際には関係ありません ヘッダーは使用しません
So, you could probably skip doing this altogether.
この作業を 完全にスキップすることもできます
The waypoints for that lane should be the waypoints from your base waypoints but
車線のウェイポイントは ベース ウェイポイントからのウェイポイントになりますが
sliced so that it goes from your closest index to
分割されています  最も近いインデックスから最も近いインデックスになりますが
the closest index plus however many would look ahead points you want.
多くの場合 ポイントを先読みします
That makes sense. Do we have to worry about doing a modular on this in case it goes over?
これはわかります終わった場合に モジュラー化することを心配する必要がありますか?
We don't. Because python slicing is really nice.
いいえPython のスライスは本当にすばらしいからです
So, if closest index plus look ahead at
最も近いインデックスとウェイポイントの予測が
waypoints is bigger than the total length of waypoints,
ウェイポイントの合計長よりも大きい場合は
it'll just give us the slides from closest index to the end.
最も近いインデックスから最後までのスライドが表示されます
Yeah, I actually noticed that when I was writing project myself,
実際に私が自分でプロジェクトを書いていたときに気づいた点ですが
that when you're near the end of the list,
リストの終わりに近づいた際に
all of a sudden,
突然
your waypoints are getting smaller and smaller
車が前進するにつれて ウェイポイントは
and smaller as you're driving the car forward,
ますます小さくなり
it all of a sudden stops at the very end of the list.
リストの最後で急停止します
Guess that reflects closely to what's actually going on in test slot two.
これは テスト スロット 2 で実際に行われていることとよく似ています
Yep, and actually, this is why in the previous part
実際には これが前の部分で扱った
when we were trying to figure out whether the waypoint was the head of the car,
wウェイポイントが車の先端であるかどうかを判断しようとしたとき
we used the closest waypoint and the waypoint behind it.
最も近いウェイポイントとその後ろのウェイポイントを使用した理由です
Because if you use the closest waypoint and the waypoint ahead of it
ウェイポイントリストの最後に近づくにつれて
as you get close to the end of the waypoints lists,
最も近いウェイポイントとそれより先のウェイポイントを使用すると
you tend to run in trouble.
問題が発生する可能性が高くなります
Cool. I think that's it for the waypoint updater.
素晴らしいウェイポイント アップデーターのためだと思います
Yeah. Once you finish this code,
はいこのコードが完成したら
you should be able to start ROS,
ROS を起動して
and then open up a new tab in your terminal or open up a new terminal window,
端末に新しいタブを開くか 新しい端末ウィンドウを開いて
source your devel environment.
開発環境を起動します
So, develsetup.sh and then try echoing final waypoints.
develsetup.sh を起動し 最終ウェイポイントをエコーします
So, ROS topic echo slash find
ROS トピック エコー スラッシュはウェイポイントを見つけて
a waypoints and make sure that this note is publishing the final waypoints that you need.
このメモが必要とする最後のウェイポイントを公開していることを確認してください
Also, I'm a very visual person.
私はとても視覚的な人です
So, when I was doing this project I wanted to be able to see those waypoints,
このプロジェクトをやっていたとき ウェイポイントを目で見えるようにしたかったので
so I actually modified the simulator to make sure that I can see them.
実際にシミュレーターを修正して ウェイポイントを視覚化しました
So, that could be like a first verification check is once you do all this,
それで 最初の検証チェックは
go ahead and boot up the simulator and see if you can
これらの作業をすべて行ってから シミュレーターを起動して
see those green orbs floating around your car.
緑色の球体が車の周りに浮かんでいるのを確認できるかどうかを確認するのと同じようなものです
So, that's it for the first part.
前半部分は終了です
All right, thanks. We'll see you next time.
ありがとうございますまた お会いしましょう